John Ireland papers, Inclusive: 1888-1901, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
John Ireland papers
Inclusive: 1888-1901, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
468
Ireland, John, 1827 - 1896
1 document box.
The John Ireland papers contain personal correspondence, land deeds, and literary productions pertaining to former Texas Governor John Ireland and his properties in Jones County, Texas.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
John Ireland was a man known for his public service and political activism. The son of Patrick and Rachel Newton Ireland, John was born in Millerstown, Kentucky, on 1827 January 21. As a young man, Ireland engaged in local enforcement, serving as both the constable and sheriff of his home county.
Ireland began studying law in 1851 at the age of twenty-four, passed the bar exam, and came to Texas, where he established a law firm in Seguin. Ireland’s reputation grew in Seguin to such a degree that within five years of his arrival, he had secured the position of mayor. As the representative of that town, Ireland attended the Secession Convention of 1861 and supported a break from the Union. An ardent Southerner, Ireland left his political and legal careers and volunteered as a private in the Confederate Army the following year. He eventually advanced to the rank of lieutenant colonel and was stationed on the Texas coast at the end of the war in 1865.
After the war, Ireland served as a member of the Texas Constitutional Convention of 1866 and became a district judge from 1866 to 1867. Despite his removal from this position for impeding Reconstruction, John was elected to the House of Representatives in 1872 and then to the Senate of the Fourteenth Legislature. He served as an associate justice of the Texas Supreme Court until the Constitution of 1876 reduced the size of this judicial body. He failed in his attempts to win a seat in the U.S. Senate (1876) as well as the U.S. House of Representatives (1878).
Ireland was elected governor of Texas in 1882 and reelected in 1884. His administration was defined by the fence-cutting war of 1883 and strikes organized by the Knights of Labor in 1885 and 1886. It was also during his administration that the University of Texas was established and construction on the Texas State Capitol was begun. In 1887, Ireland once again lost his bid to serve in the U.S. Senate. After retiring from the political sphere, Ireland practiced law in Seguin until he died on 1896 March 18.
This collection deals primarily with Ireland’s properties in Jones County, Texas, (2,573 acres) and the execution of his will. Problems arose from the fact that Ireland was the legal guardian of his grandson, Ireland Graves. Graves was only a fifteen year old minor when Ireland passed away. A dispute in the courts arose as to whom would be best suited to assume Ireland Graves’ guardianship and administer the land that he inherited.
Scope and Content
The John Ireland papers range from 1888 to 1901 and do not encompass any of his gubernatorial works. Instead, the materials deal primarily with his land investments in Jones County, Texas, and the execution of his will.
Arrangement
This small collection has been organized into three series: I. Correspondence, II. Legal Documents, and III. Literary Productions. The correspondence, comprised of two folders, is organized chronologically. The legal documents and literary productions are organized according to the type of material.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 468. Acquired 1972-12-04
Related Resources
Related references
Elliott, Claude. “John Ireland.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2012 February 27.
Hendrickson, Jr., Kenneth E. The Chief Executives of Texas: From Stephen F. Austin to John B. Connally, Jr. College Station, TX: Texas A&M University Press, 1995.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Ireland, John.
Places
Texas -- History -- 19th century.; Texas -- History -- 20th century.; Texas -- History.
Subjects
Governors -- Texas.
Genres
Correspondence.; Deeds.; Maps.; Transcriptions (documents).
- Correspondence, 1888-1901; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  These folders contain general correspondence written to and from Governor John Ireland. The letters relate to Ireland’s land investments and the execution of his will. There are also a number of transcriptions of letters exchanged between John Ireland and A.J. Fry. This series is in good condition.
  - Letters: General, 1888-1900 October (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters: General, 1900 November-1901 March (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters: General, 1901 April-August (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Transcriptions: A.J. Fry, 1888-1891 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Legal Documents, 1890-1901; 2
  This series is comprised of two folders relating to Governor Ireland’s land investments in Jones County, Texas, as well as the execution of his will. These materials are directly related to the correspondence from the previous series. These materials are in good condition.
  - Deeds: General, 1890-1897 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Deeds: General, 1900-1901 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Literary Productions, 1895-1896, undated; 3
  This series consists of a map of Ireland’s plot of land located in Jones County, Texas, as well as notes concerning the dimensions of his property. Transcriptions recently added to the collection contain articles pertaining to Ireland’s funeral and the general state of Texas. These materials are in good condition.
  - Map: Jones County, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Notes: Jones County, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Transcriptions: Articles: Obituaries: John Ireland, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Transcriptions: Clipping: San Antonio Daily Light, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Transcriptions: Essay: Headright System, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Transcriptions: Marginalia: Fry Family Bible, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)